<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: flatiron | A Computer Walks Into A Bar]]></title>
  <link href="http://computerwalksintobar.com/blog/categories/flatiron/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://computerwalksintobar.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-23T09:51:05-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://computerwalksintobar.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Amanda Chang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Balancing Beauty and the Technological World]]></title>
    <link href="http://computerwalksintobar.com/blog/2015/05/13/balancing-beauty-and-the-technological-world/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-13T11:03:15-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://computerwalksintobar.com/blog/2015/05/13/balancing-beauty-and-the-technological-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/stars.png"></p>

<p>Last week, I went stargazing.</p>

<p>I live in New York City, so I couldn&rsquo;t see many stars, unfortunately. But as my eyes became accustomed to the shades of the night, a few dim specks of light emerged from the seemingly endless fog. As I breathed in the crisp late April evening, I felt present. I was <em>there</em>.</p>

<p>In today&rsquo;s society of constant connection, I find that I often forget to take time out of my day to appreciate my surroundings. I&rsquo;ve passed away numerous hours clicking through an endless loop of social media websites – Facebook, to Twitter, to Pinterest, to YouTube, back to Facebook. Subway rides are filled with podcasts, music, audiobooks. I rarely have to experience boredom, but I&rsquo;ve also let precious moments slip by without notice.</p>

<p>In spite of my reflections on presentness, I really enjoy my career as a web developer. Coding is a creative activity that allows us to build tools greater than ourselves – and I&rsquo;ve been interested in computers and technology for as long as I can remember. Even my elementary school assignments were typed in Microsoft Creative Writer. So how can I balance my love of programming with a feeling that the way that we consume technology is just not right?</p>

<h2>The Problem with Instant Access</h2>

<p>When I was in college, I dated a guy whose Blackberry was almost an extension of his arm. We would frequently eat meals together, as couples do, and he would often get distracted upon receiving an email. &ldquo;Hold on,&rdquo; he would say, &ldquo;This email is time-sensitive.&rdquo; In retrospect, I&rsquo;ve realized that it was in fact the conversations that were truly time-sensitive. I&rsquo;m 100% sure that all of the emails were still there once our face-to-face conversations were over.</p>

<p>The topic of our networked society and its effects is common among modern research – such as social psychologist Sherry Turkle&rsquo;s book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Alone-Together-Expect-Technology-Other/dp/0465031463"><em>Alone Together</em></a> (2011). According to Turkle, interactions like the aforementioned are prevalent. Turkle, who works at MIT, says <a href="http://www.apa.org/monitor/2011/06/social-networking.aspx">in an interview</a>, &ldquo;The idea that we should put each other on pause as though we were machines in order to attend to those who are not present has become commonplace. It needs to be examined. I don’t think that is how we want to treat each other.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Furthermore, the ease at which we can interact on a surface level often reduces the urgency with which we seek out deeper interactions. Turkle states, &ldquo;We Facebook-friend people who do not know their commitment to us and similarly, we are unsure of what commitment we have to them. They can, in fact, be more like &lsquo;fans&rsquo; than friends. But their presence can sustain us and distract us and make it less likely for us to look beyond them to other social encounters. They can provide the illusion of companionship without the demands of friendship, without the demands of intimacy.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Many agree with the idea that social networks actually distance us from meaningful relationships. In fact, if you visit Google and type in &ldquo;social media creates,&rdquo; the first autocomplete hit is &ldquo;social media creates <strong>isolation</strong>.&rdquo;</p>

<h2>Appearing Alright</h2>

<p>A relatively recent story that really stuck with me is that of the tragic suicide of Madison Holleran, a 19-year-old track runner at UPenn. Madison took her life in January 2014, by jumping off of a nine-story parking garage. <a href="http://espn.go.com/espn/feature/story/_/id/12833146/instagram-account-university-pennsylvania-runner-showed-only-part-story">A recent article</a> published in <em>ESPN</em> magazine illustrates that Madison&rsquo;s social media pages &ldquo;concealed her reality.&rdquo; The article reads:</p>

<blockquote><p>THE LIFE MADISON projected on her own Instagram feed was filled with shots that seemed to confirm everyone&rsquo;s expectations: Of course she was loving her first year of college. Of course she enjoyed running. Her mom remembers looking at a photo on her feed and saying, &ldquo;Madison, you look like you&rsquo;re so happy at this party.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;Mom,&rdquo; Madison said. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s just a picture.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>As we maintain our Facebook and Instagram accounts, we generally only share the positive aspects of our lives, the parts we <em>want</em> to broadcast. This creates a problem when we start to contrast our lives – and all of the problems within them – and the seemingly-perfect &ldquo;lives&rdquo; that our friends display. We begin to feel alone in our mixed emotions; we forget that sadness, like joy, is universal.</p>

<center><img src="/images/insta.png" width="400"><br><em>My latest Instagram photo – my filtered life</em></center>


<p>The <em>ESPN</em> article compares this phenomenon to Instagram itself:</p>

<blockquote><p>With Instagram, one thing has changed: the amount we consume of one another&rsquo;s edited lives. Young women growing up on Instagram are spending a significant chunk of each day absorbing others&#8217; filtered images while they walk through their own realities, unfiltered. In a recent survey conducted by the Girl Scouts, nearly 74 percent of girls agreed that other girls tried to make themselves look &ldquo;cooler than they are&rdquo; on social networking sites.</p></blockquote>

<p>I&rsquo;m not preaching against Instagram – I have fun documenting as much as the next person. But I think we should work a little harder to spread awareness that Instagram real is not <em>real</em> real. And we should remember that anything in excess is dangerous; social media is no exception.</p>

<center><img src="/images/unfiltered.png" width="400"></center>


<h2>Being Responsible Consumers</h2>

<p>Like I said before, I love technology.</p>

<p>And I love my job, as a web development instructor at <a href="http://flatironschool.com/">The Flatiron School</a>. The opportunity to teach driven adults to empower themselves is so rewarding – the best way to renew someone&rsquo;s excitement about life is to give them a superpower, and I feel like coding is that. It&rsquo;s problem-solving, innovating. It&rsquo;s <em>fun</em>.</p>

<p>Another company that we frequently work with is <a href="https://www.dosomething.org">DoSomething.org</a>. DoSomething.org describes itself as &ldquo;one of the largest global orgs for young people and social change, our 3.6 million members tackle campaigns that impact every cause, from poverty to violence to the environment to literally everything else.&rdquo; In my opinion, the organization uses the power of technology and social media in the perfect way – to extend its reach and inspire people to impact positive social change.</p>

<center>&#8212;</center>


<p>While discussing this topic with a friend the other day, he pointed out an interesting phenomenon. On the F train in Brooklyn, there&rsquo;s a point at which the train comes above ground. If you look out the window, you can see the Statue of Liberty. And the kids do – while the adults always pull out their phones.</p>

<p>Just like anything, consuming technology (even for us engineers) is all about balance. So I&rsquo;m issuing myself a challenge: to notice one new thing each day. Feel free to join me :) We can strive for a future full of innovation – but let&rsquo;s try not to forget beauty.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What I've Learned About Life Through Teaching Adults To Code]]></title>
    <link href="http://computerwalksintobar.com/blog/2015/03/14/what-ive-learned-about-life-through-teaching-adults-to-code/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-14T19:14:43-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://computerwalksintobar.com/blog/2015/03/14/what-ive-learned-about-life-through-teaching-adults-to-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/EKbG8et.jpg" alt="Dance Lesson at Flatiron!" /></p>

<p>Yesterday marks the end of my eighth week as a web development instructor at the <a href="http://flatironschool.com/">Flatiron School</a>. I feel immensely lucky for the chance to work with such a driven group of coworkers and students &ldquo;<a href="https://twitter.com/aviflombaum/status/575456180455124992">to align education with reality</a>.&rdquo; In honor of this two-month-iversary, here are a few things I&rsquo;ve learned:</p>

<h2>Being a Beginner Takes Courage</h2>

<p>Six months ago, I enrolled at Flatiron after a year of freelancing as a theater lighting designer. As a 23-year-old New Yorker, many of my friends are still in the &ldquo;transition&rdquo; period; they&rsquo;re either looking to become more established in their chosen fields or working subpar jobs to gain experience and open more exciting doors. Even given my relatively short stint working in theater and my young group of friends, the career shift felt like a huge one.</p>

<p>In contrast, many of my students left long, successful careers to learn to code full-time. I can&rsquo;t imagine what that must feel like, but having seen the positive change in some of my classmates who did the same, I know that the payoff can be enormous. For me, every day is a reminder that the best things in life come from hard work and struggle.</p>

<h2>A Positive (Or Negative) Attitude Is Contagious</h2>

<p>Last week, <a href="https://twitter.com/S2K10">Seiji</a>, one of my students, organized &ldquo;Club Euler,&rdquo; essentially a student study group that meets half an hour before school to work through complex puzzles. Half an hour before school means extending an already rigorous day of 9-6 coding to begin at 8:30 in the morning. In spite of the early morning and the time commitment, most of the class chose to attend Club Euler twice last week.</p>

<p>I think the high interest reflects both the inherent intellectual curiosity of our students and the sense of community that Flatiron fosters. Being a student and then a coworker at Flatiron reminded me that the success of a team feels much greater than personal achievements do.</p>

<h2>There Is Always More To Learn</h2>

<p>In life, most careers/hobbies/activities have some limiting factor. Team sports and theater are limited by other people – you can&rsquo;t play soccer or direct <em>Hamlet</em> without a team on board. Art and cooking are limited by supplies; once you run out of paint, you&rsquo;re done painting. In a way, I feel like coding is less restrictive than many other things. Once you make the initial investment and get a computer, you have access to the limitless ability to learn and to code (sure, you need electricity for battery, but that&rsquo;s easy).</p>

<p>When I was working in theater, a more experienced designer, <a href="http://www.reidthompsondesign.com/">Reid Thompson</a>, gave me excellent advice: be a sponge. Working in web development makes this so easy, as code is constantly evolving. I try to learn something new every day!</p>

<h2>The Bottom Line</h2>

<p>All in all, I am thrilled that my first full-time job constantly demonstrates how important it is to <strong>strive for happiness–your own and that of the people around you.</strong> Can&rsquo;t wait to see what new lessons the next two months have in store!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hackers and Theater-Makers]]></title>
    <link href="http://computerwalksintobar.com/blog/2015/03/14/hackers-and-theater-makers/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-14T14:21:07-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://computerwalksintobar.com/blog/2015/03/14/hackers-and-theater-makers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post was originally published on the <a href="http://blog.flatironschool.com/hackers-and-theater-makers-code-as-a-creative/">Flatiron School Blog</a>.</em></p>

<p>When I decided to enroll at the <a href="http://flatironschool.com/">Flatiron School</a> and shift my career from theater lighting design to web development, I worried unnecessarily that I would lose my drive to create. In practice, I constantly meet other developers with creative passions. My mentor, who I met through the <a href="http://blog.flatironschool.com/post/107229276393/fog-creek-and-the-nyc-web-development-fellowship">Fog Creek Fellowship</a>, is also a musician who keeps guitars in his office. One of my current Flatiron School students used to be a curator. The list goes on.</p>

<p>The fact that I&rsquo;ve met a surprisingly large number of creative people in the NYC tech community may be explained by an essay written by programmer and writer Paul Graham entitled &ldquo;<a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/hp.html">Hackers and Painters</a>,&rdquo; which was one of the first readings assigned to me as a Flatiron School student. In his essay, Graham enumerates the similarities between computer programming and art. He explains:</p>

<blockquote><p><em>What hackers and painters have in common is that they&rsquo;re both makers. Along with composers, architects, and writers, what hackers and painters are trying to do is make good things.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Graham makes a number of excellent points in his essay; hackers and painters do indeed share many traits. However, I see a few key differences between web developers and painters that imply web development may in fact be more akin to theater-making than to painting.</p>

<h2>Development Is Collaborative</h2>

<p>Although programming is often thought of as a solitary activity, I haven&rsquo;t found that stereotype to be true. Working with my peers on final projects was one of the most valuable experiences from my time as a Flatiron School student. Each member of the group brought a unique perspective, as well as a different set of strengths.</p>

<p>The benefits of working with others to complete a task are articulated in dancer and choreographer Twyla Tharp&rsquo;s book <em><a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Collaborative-Habit-Lessons-Together/dp/1416576517">The Collaborative Habit</a></em>. In the book, Tharp explains how collaboration inherently grants new insight:</p>

<blockquote><p><em>As a practical reality, let&rsquo;s look at collaboration with a single partner. We bounce ideas off another person. Then the other person volleys them back to us. That exchange makes us hear our ideas with new ears for the simplest of reasons—what our partners say is not a literal repetition of what we said.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Theater at its core is a collaborative art form. Most successful production staffs include a director, a set designer, a lighting designer, a costume designer, and a sound designer, all working closely to realize the same vision. I&rsquo;ve learned that a team full of talented specialists creates a spark. As Tharp states, &ldquo;People in a good collaboration accomplish more than the group&rsquo;s most talented members could achieve on their own.&rdquo;</p>

<p>The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open-source_movement">open-source movement</a> relies on this philosophy that multiple people working on different aspects of a project creates something greater than the sum of the individual parts. As I&rsquo;m writing this blog post, Rails has 2,596 contributors on <a href="http://github.com/rails/rails">GitHub</a>. Many tech companies have their developers program in <a href="http://collaboration.csc.ncsu.edu/laurie/Papers/XPSardinia.PDF">pairs</a>, in order to optimize efficiency, learning, and satisfaction and minimize code defects. And just recently, one of my Flatiron students declared, &ldquo;It&rsquo;s so rewarding to see how others at my table approach a problem. They think about it in completely different ways than I do.&rdquo;</p>

<h2>Application Evolve With Their Users</h2>

<p>Unlike most paintings, works of theater continue to evolve even after they are revealed to an audience. What results is a living, breathing work of art that responds to human interaction. In his monumental book <em><a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Empty-Space-Theatre-Immediate/dp/0684829576">The Empty Space</a></em>, theater and film director Peter Brook outlines an experiment in audience influence, involving an amateur actor reading a speech from Henry V:</p>

<blockquote><p><em>The amateur actor was to read the speech again, stopping for a moment after each name: the audience was to endeavour silently in the pause to recall and put together its impressions of Auschwitz and Agincourt, to try to find a way of believing that these names were once individuals, as vividly as if the butchery had occurred in living memory&hellip;Now the audience’s concentration began to guide [the actor]: his inflexions were simple, his rhythms true: this in turn increased the audience’s interest and so the two-way current began to flow. When this was ended, no explanations were needed, the audience had seen itself in action, it had seen how many layers silence can contain.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Professional theater productions hold open &ldquo;previews&rdquo; before the official opening night. These previews allow the team to continue shaping the show based on audience response.</p>

<p>Similarly, most web applications continue to grow even after they are deployed. Here at the Flatiron School, students present their projects to their classmates and instructors throughout the building process, in order to get feedback from potential users.</p>

<h2>But Why Does This Matter?</h2>

<p>What I think developers, painters, and theater-makers all have in common is the desire to understand and contribute to the human experience. In order to do that, we must absorb our surroundings and let every interaction influence our work. In &ldquo;Hackers and Painters,&rdquo; Graham writes:</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Empathy is probably the single most important difference between a good hacker and a great one. Some hackers are quite smart, but when it comes to empathy are practically solipsists. It&rsquo;s hard for such people to design great software, because they can&rsquo;t see things from the user&rsquo;s point of view.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Developers can learn about empathy through great works of theater, and theater-makers can uncover truths about humanity through the ways in which people interact with applications. Regardless of our medium or our motivations—to make  life more convenient, more beautiful, more entertaining—artists and programmers alike create for a better world.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
